hello welcome to another video of C
snippet this is going to be a
continuation of last video where we are
looking into string data jpa in the last
video we have looked into the
introduction part of it we have
understood what is jdbc what is om and
what is ring data jpa now in this video
we are actually going to dive deep
inside jpa architecture and entity life
cycle so this is going to be a fun video
so sit back relax and enjoy the show so
let's first go through the agenda of
this particular video so this is
basically the agenda so spring data jpa
right in the last video we have seen
this introduction right so we have seen
what is jdbc what is orm what is jpa we
have understood everything right so the
prerequisite of this particular video is
basically go ahead and check that
particular video so just a quick recap
we have seen what is the jdbc
connections right we have seen what
exactly is om right we have understood
jpa and spring data jpa there right now
if I come back over here then in this
video we are going to look into jpa
architecture and and entity life cycle
right so implementing spring data jpa is
very easy part right it is very easy you
will have to write very less code in
order to implement that and it is very
straightforward right but what exactly
is happening behind the scene that is
something you need to understand right
so that is why I am covering jpa
architecture and entity life cycle over
here in this video so here we are going
to understand important concept inside
jpa right we are going to get familiar
with all the terminologies that we have
over here so we will first see the
architecture we will see life cycle and
we'll understand the internals of jpa
right so that is basically about your
agenda right now let's get started now
if I go to this canvas so if you
remember in the last video we have seen
this om right so we discussed that this
object which is a Java object will be
mapped to your table right so we were
discussing that your Java object will be
mapped to the table inside your database
right now when we Define this Java
object which is a mapping to that
particular table inside your DB then
this particular object is called as a
entity it is basically a Java object
which is mapped to your relational
database table right so when we look
into jpa architecture let's start from
entity which is a object which will be
mapped to table inside your relational
database right so in this video whenever
we refer to entity just think of it as a
Java object which will be saved inside
your table right for example if you go
over here then I have sample project
over here this is a e-commerce project
that that we have used multiple time
inside this particular Series right so
you might be aware of it already if you
are following so if you see over here
you have this entity and for example you
have this product entity over here right
so this is how we Define a product
entity it is nothing but a plain Java
class these annotations and everything
we are going to actually look into when
we actually see the implementation right
this is just example of entity that I'm
showing you over here right it will just
have Fields like ID name price
description stock all of these fields
will be there inside the table right so
all these fields will be actually column
inside your table and this will
basically be the table name right so
that is how so this is basically Java
object which will be a table right now
how this entity will be saved inside
your database so what is the Journey of
this entity to this database right so
that is something which we are going to
highlight over here right and there is a
life cycle of this particular entity as
well that we are going to look into so
all these things that you see on this
side is basically inside your
application and and your application is
basically connecting to database right
now this particular entity will be
mapped to a table inside this particular
database right how it will be mapped all
these things comes into picture when we
look into jpa right so as I already told
you entity is basically the object which
maps to table inside your database right
this entity will be managed by a entity
manager right so entity manager comes
into picture over here another
terminology entity manager right now
what is entity manager as a name says
entity manager is basically a interface
inside Java which is responsible for
managing entities so whatever entities
you create all of them will be managed
by this guy over here think of it as a
manager who manages these entities so
inside your application you will have
multiple entities all these entities
will be managed by your entity manager
so all the operations that you are going
to do on this particular entity for
example let's say save right or persist
who will do that that operation will be
done by entity manager so you will
actually create object of entity manager
and you will say entity manager. persist
persist this entity right and all other
operations like remove merge find all
these operations will be maintained by
this entity manager over here it is kind
of a responsibility of entity manager to
perform operations on entity right and
who creates this entity manager
basically entity manager Factory is
responsible for creating entity manager
so entity manager Factory will generally
be one Factory per application and which
will be managed by persistence right so
in your application the configuration
will be managed by something called as
persistence.xml right that will
basically create entity manager Factory
which will be one Factory and it can
create multiple entity managers inside
your application which will manage all
the entities inside your application
right so this persistence.xml and
everything is something which we Define
in jpa okay this is something which we
do not need inside spring data jpa but
in order to understand spring data jpa
we need to understand jpa first and this
is basically the architecture of jpa
what happens inside jpa right because
spring data jpa is just abstraction on
top of jpa as we have looked into last
video right spring data jpa is just a
layer on top of jpa internally it will
use all these things only right it will
use entity entity manager Factory and
everything right that is why it is
important to understand that right so
till now we have seen all these things
right entity we know entity manager and
entity manager Factory and persistence
right so this this is basically this is
also called as persistence unit right
what we are going to do now let's uh
jump to the left hand side of it now
next thing let's look into is
persistence context right so this is
very very important right what is
persistence context right now think of a
persistence context as a cache as a
cache where these entities will be
stored these entities will be stored
here temporarily right inside a
persistence context consider it as a bag
inside which you have this entities
stored on temporary bases and this guy
entity manager is interacting with this
persistence context to get those
entities right to get those entities so
to reiterate persistence context is kind
of a cache where all your entities will
be stored and managed right so this
picture will be cleared more when we
actually look into this particular
entity life cycle right now let's say we
have entity created we have stored it in
persistence context this guy is ready
and we hit something like persist right
what this guy will do entity manager
entity manager will call persist right
it will say entity manager. persist and
it will try to save this entity now
entity manager is kind of an interface
right entity manager cannot interact
with database what it will do it will
have some kind of a provider provider do
you remember from the last video we have
hibernate or few other Frameworks so if
you see over here in the or we have seen
hibernate Eclipse link or open jpa as a
providers right so internally jpa will
use hibernate if you see over here jpa
will use hibernate right so what this
guy will do this guy will offload the
task of interacting with database to
hibernate right now hibernate will have
its own queries hi bernet will create
queries right will have its own query
language depending on what entity
manager is asking or telling it will
create the SQL queries hi bernet will
create the SQL queries and hit on the
database and entity manager will also
create the transactions so transaction
also will be managed over here right so
spring transaction is something which we
have already covered so if you remember
that video we have already talked about
the persistence context in that video
right so basically transaction will be
created and all the database operations
will happen inside this particular
transaction which will be managed by
your entity manager and everything like
transaction managers and everything
comes into picture that we have already
seen you haven't seen that video I
recommend you go ahead and check that
you will have in-depth understanding
ofing transactions so that is what is
happening behind the scene when we
actually ask entities to be persistent
right now just to show you the example
right I have this existing project again
eom application right if you see over
here then we have this product service
and in product service we have something
called as ADD product uh which will save
inside a repository right now this is
jpa we are using but internally inside
jpa you will have something called as
entity manager so this is basically
internal method simple jpa repository
and here if you see we have entity
manager. persist right so if you see
over here this is basically entity
manager that we are talking about over
here right if you see over here it is
actually calling persist and when this
guy call persist after that all these
things will happen these hibernate
related things right all these things
will come into picture the transactions
the queries will be created and will
actually the queries on your database
like that it will happen right we are
going to come back to it when we
actually see the implementation right it
is just a glance kind of a trailer right
so that is basically your jpa now let's
come back over here to entity right so
what is the life cycle of entity what
all things it will go through right now
let me just bring that up entity life
cycle if you scroll over here then you
will have it here right there we go I
hope it is visible let me Zoom it a bit
so this is basically the life cycle of
your entity right now these are the
states of your entities right so
transient manage removed detached and uh
this is basically the database this is
not a state right transient is a state
managed is a state removed detached all
these are states right so whenever you
create new entity right for example you
are creating a new entity let's say you
are creating it from a controller or you
are creating it with a new keyword let's
say so let's say here you are creating a
new application right application means
let's say job application right because
when we are going to look into
implementation we will actually see
application management project right so
job application management project so if
you see over here we have already this
application management system project
created right but it do not have
anything right we are actually going to
write everything from scratch when we
see the implementation but let's see now
right let's say we are creating a new
application now when we create a new
application now let's say application is
entity right for example let me just
quickly create a entity for us over here
what I will do I will just go over here
create a new uh Java class right and
let's say
application or let's say applicant right
applicant basically the person who is
applying so that uh this is basically
the entity so applicant details we will
store inside database let's say right so
here let's say we we have few details so
let me just add few details real quick
so let's say we have ID name email and
phone number of this particular
applicant right so this is basically the
entity for us so this is kind of a
entity for us right
so basically uh instead of application
let's say applicant now since we have
created applicant so let's say we are
creating a new applicant right now this
is a traditional way of creating object
inside Java so let's say we are creating
the entity like this for now right now
the moment we create the entity inside
the application it will be inside the
transient state right this is basically
the state of your new entity right now
whenever this entity is in transient
state it is kind of a fresh entity right
so it is not managed by your entity
manager yet so your entity manager is
not managing it yet right so when your
entity manager will manage it the moment
you call persist on it whenever I say
entity manager. persist it will be a
managed entity managed by whom who
manages the entity as we have seen
entity manager manages it that means
this will be now a managed entity since
we called persist on it right so how
this transition from transient to manage
will happen by using entity manager.
persist as we have seen over here right
we have seen over here in this project
that we have this entity manager. purist
right so whenever we call this the bean
state will be converted from transient
to managed right so now the Bean is in
managed state right and whenever the
Bean is in managed state it will be
associated with persistence context that
means this Bean will be be added inside
your persistence context that's why this
state is also called as persistence
State as well as we add as this will be
added inside persistence context so if
you remember here we have persistence
context and entity manager will usually
interact with persistence context to get
the entities right managed entities so
basically persistence context will store
managed entities right not all the
entities but only managed entities which
we want to persist right now when your
entity is in in manage state if you make
any changes to that particular entity it
will be automatically synchronized with
your database right will be synchronized
with your database and it will actually
saved inside a DB when we actually flush
it that means when we do transaction
commit right your transaction will be
completed and your data will be added
over here and if in case we are finding
something we are finding a entity inside
your database then that particular
entity will be created and it will be in
managed state right after that we have
have detached right we have detached
state right now what is detached so the
entities which are in detached those
entities were once in persistence
context but now they are no longer
managed by your entity manager right so
basically once you detach The Entity or
close or clear it will not be managed by
your persistence context and will be in
detached state right and if you want to
move it back to in manage St then you
will have something called as merge
operation which you can do in order to
move it back to managed state in order
to make them manageable by your entity
manager right so that is basically
detached state right now the last state
over here is basically removed state
right now let's say when your entity is
marked for deletion you have some you
have this applicant entity which is
marked for deletion but it is still
inside your persistence context right
and it is ready to be deleted once you
commit your transaction once you flush
it it will be deleted from your database
right so once we call this remove
operation your entity will be
transitioned from manage to your removed
state right and when we commit the
transaction it will be removed from your
database right that is basically the
entire flow so this is basically how the
transition from each state will happen
right whenever you create a new
applicant it will be in transient State
and you call entity manager. persist or
save it will be transferred to
persistant or manage State rate once you
call detach or let's say entity manager
closes explicitly then it will be moved
from this manage to detach state from
persistent to detach state right or if
you call remove function right remove
function from entity manager on any
entity then it will be moved from
persistent to removed so like this right
and it will come back to persistance
from detach from here to here if we call
merge method on entity manager right so
that is basically how the flow of entity
manager actually works right so that is
basically overall life cycle of your
entities right so that is basically for
this particular video so we have seen
jpa architecture and entity manager life
cycle over here we have understood the
basics of it now in the next video we
are actually going to write the code
inside this particular application so we
are going to implement this application
management system right we are going to
create few entities we are going to uh
add repository by using jpa we we are
actually going to use H2 database in
order to implement that and we are going
to get our hands dirty with the code
right so implementation part we are
going to look into next video so just a
quick glance or agenda of that
particular video so we are going to set
up this particular project I've already
created a project over here I will
highlight how to create that how we can
create entities by using different
annotations after that we will see how
to create repositories what are
different type of repositories inside
spring data jpa we will see inbuilt
methods for crud operations what all
inbuilt method are provided by spring
data jpa those method we will see very
very easy stuff for that we will see
query method what exactly is query
method we will see at the rate query
annotation so lot more things are coming
into picture when we actually see spring
data jpa and its implementation right so
stay tuned for that video if you don't
want to miss that subscribe to code
snippet now that's it for this video if
you like the video hit the like button
share this video with your friends so
that they are also aware of jpa
architecture and entity life cycle
that's for this video see you in the
next video